Guide to the Greenpoint Petroleum Remediation Project (GPRP) Records BCMS.0062
Brooklyn Collection
Greenpoint Petroleum Remediation Project (GPRP) Records
1995-2015
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0062
5.9 Linear feet 13 document boxes and 1 binder.
Documentation of the Greenpoint Petroleum Remediation Project deposited at Brooklyn Public Library for public record.
Historical Note
This history of the Greenpoint Petroleum Remediation Project is excerpted from the NYSDEC website.
The northeast area of Greenpoint, between North Henry Street, Norman Avenue, and Newtown Creek, has been heavily industrialized and the site of various petroleum industries for over 140 years. Oil refining operations date back to 1834 with the refining of whale oil. According to one published report, petroleum refining operations began as early as 1854, with the production of kerosene, as naptha and gasoline were considered by-products of the refining process. By 1870 over 50 refineries were located along the banks of Newtown Creek and by 1892, the majority of the area refineries were purchased and consolidated into the Standard Oil Trust. Around 1900, gasoline and fuel oils became the dominant product refined or stored in terminal facilities in the Greenpoint area. Following the breakup of the Trust in 1911, ownership of the refinery property in Greenpoint reverted to the Standard Oil Company of New York (SOCONY) and these operations became the SOCONY (later Mobil Oil Corporation) Brooklyn Refinery. The refinery reportedly had a capacity to refine over 33,000 barrels (1.4 million gallons) of crude oil a day and produced fuel oils, gasoline, kerosene, and refinery oil. Also stored within the former refinery were petroleum additives and miscellaneous refining by-products.
On September 2, 1978, the U. S. Coast Guard was making a routine helicopter patrol of Newtown Creek when it noticed the signs of an oil spill entering Newtown Creek from the area at the end of Meeker Avenue. A subsequent investigation concluded that the area of the spill under the Greenpoint area was in excess of 52 acres and the total spill volume, as estimated in 1979, was approximately 17 million gallons of petroleum products.
Petroleum product recovery operations are currently being conducted within five distinct areas: the former ExxonMobil Terminal, the KM Terminal, the commercial/industrial/residential area southwest of the KM Terminal known as the ExxonMobil Off-Site Plume, the site of the former Paragon Oil Terminal, which is currently the location of the Peerless Importers/Empire Merchants distribution facility, and the Apollo Street Creek Parcels located between the KM Terminal and the site of the former Paragon Oil Terminal. Product recovery systems have been in place since 1979. ExxonMobil entered into two consent orders with NYSDEC in 1990 and began upgrades to its recovery systems, including the design and construction of a new and expanded system to recover free product from the Off-Site Area. Following the discovery of free product seepage through the facility's bulkhead into Newtown Creek, ExxonMobil also began recovery activities at the Peerless Importers/former Paragon Oil site in February 1991. Mobil continued recovery activities until May 2005 when Texaco took over that portion of the project.
Four different free product recovery systems are currently operating in Greenpoint. These include the former ExxonMobil Terminal Recovery and Containment System (RCS), the KM Terminal Recovery System, the ExxonMobil Off-Site Plume Recovery System and the former Paragon Oil Terminal Recovery System. Significant treatment system upgrades to increase the free product recovery capacity and water treatment capabilities of all the recovery systems have been completed over the years.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of documentation of the Greenpoint Petroleum Remediation Project, which is sponsored by the ExxonMobil Refining and Supply Company (with Roux Associates), the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation (NYSDEC), and the Chevron Environmental Management Company (later Texaco, Inc. with the Science Applications International Corporation (SAIC)). The documentation includes printed reports, maps, charts, correspondence, work plans, progress and status reports, and CD-ROMs.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
This collection was deposited at Brooklyn Public Library over time by the companies involved and the NYSDEC.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Public Library's Greenpoint branch also holds documentation of the GPRP. While the Greenpoint branch is under renovation (2017-2019), the documents are available at the Leonard branch.
The New York State Department of Environmental Conservation has some documentation of the project on its website here and here.
The New York City Office of Environmental Remediation has documentation of Brooklyn projects arranged by address available here.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in three series by the organizations which produced them: ExxonMobil (through Roux Associates, Inc.), Texaco, Inc. (through Science Applications International Corporation (SAIC)), and the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation (NYSDEC). Within each series, documents are arranged in subseries by project and by date.
Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Newtown Creek (Kings County-New York County, N.Y.); Oil pollution of soils; Oil spills--Cleanup; Oil spills--Containment; Oil spills--Environmental aspects; Oil spills--Management; ChevronTexaco (Firm).; Exxon Mobil Corporation.; New York (State). Department of Environmental Conservation.; Roux Associates Inc.; Science Applications International Corporation.; Texaco, Inc.
- Series 1: ExxonMobil/Roux Associates, Inc.
  General
  This series consists of documentation of the ExxonMobil remediation efforts, including the Off- and On-Site Free-Product Recovery Systems and the Peerless Importers Containment Boom. The records are arranged in seven subseries by project and/or type. Within subseries, records are arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries 1.1: Community Progress Meetings
    - Community Progress Meetings, July & October 2000; July 2001; July & August 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Subseries 1.2: Off-Site Free-Product Recovery System
    - Progress Reports, October and November 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Operation and Maintenance Reports, April-December 1996; February-December 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
    - Operation and Maintenance Reports, February-September 2002; 4th Quarter 2002; 1st-3rd Quarter 2003; 2nd-4th Quarter 2004 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
    - Supplemental Investigation of the Off-Site Free-Product Plume, c. 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Bound Reports 1-4: Operation and Maintenance Reports, 1st & 2nd Quarter 2006; 1st & 2nd Quarter 2008 (Box 2)
    - Bound Reports 1-5: Operation and Maintenance Reports, 3rd & 4th Quarter 2008; 1st-3rd Quarter 2009 (Box 3)
    - Bound Reports 1-3: Operation and Maintenance Reports, 4th Quarter 2009; 1st & 2nd Quarters 2010 (Box 4)
  - Subseries 1.3: On-Site Free-Product Recovery System
    - Bound Reports 4-6: Operation and Maintenance Reports, 1st & 2nd Quarter 2006; 1st Quarter 2008 (Box 4)
    - Bound Reports 1-5: Operation and Maintenance Reports, 2nd-4th Quarter 2008; 1st & 2nd Quarter 2009 (Box 5)
    - Bound Reports 1-3: Operation and Maintenance Reports, 3rd & 4th Quarter 2009; 1st Quarter 2010 (Box 6)
  - Subseries 1.4: Peerless Importers Containment Boom
    - Quarterly Operation and Maintenance Reports, 2001-2005 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
    - Remedial Investigation, January 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Remedial Investigation, Appendices A-D (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Remedial Investigation, Appendix E (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Remedial Investigation, Appendices F-H (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Summary of Grout Injection IRM Pilot Study Activities (Draft), March 2005 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 1.5: SPDES/Long Island Well Permits
    - Bound Reports 1 & 2: SPDES Permit Applications, May 2007 (Box 7)
    - Bound Report 3: Long Island Well Permit Application, June 2007 (Box 7)
    - Bound Report 4: Response to NYSDEC August 3, 2007 Notice of Incomplete Application (Box 7)
    - Bound Report 5: SPDES Equivalency, September 2007 (Box 7)
    - Bound Report 6: Public Participation Plan, October 2007 (Box 7)
    - Bound Report 7: SPDES Application Overview/Public Information Meeting, November 2007 (Box 7)
    - Bound Report 8: Certificate of Completeness - Public Participation Plan, December 2007 (Box 7)
    - Discharge Permit - Draft (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 1.6: Discharge Monitoring Reports (Free Product Recovery Systems)
    - Disc 1: Digital reports on compact disc, July 2007 – June 2011 (Box 8)
    - Bound Reports 1-3, February-March 2012 (Box 8)
    - Bound Reports 4 & 5, August & September 2012 (Box 8)
    - Bound Reports 6 & 7, March & April 2013 (Box 8)
    - Bound Reports 8 & 9, July & August 2013 (Box 8)
    - Bound Reports 10-20, January-November 2014 (Box 8)
  - Subseries 1.7: Miscellaneous Reports
    - Bound Report 1: Engineering Evaluation of the Soil Vapor Extraction System Operation, September 2010 (Box 9)
    - Bound reports 2-4: Acute Whole Effluent Toxicity Testing Reports, May-September 2015 (Box 9)
- Series 2: Texaco, Inc./SAIC
  This series consists of documentation of the Texaco (formerly Chevron) remediation efforts at the Former Paragon Oil Terminal (Bridgewater Street; Chevron/Texaco Facility #304209) and the 100-120 Apollo Street Property. The records are arranged in two subseries by type. Within subseries/boxes, records are arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries 2.1: General Project Documentation
    - Bound Report 5: Transmittal of Information Package from Project Teleconference, June 12 2006 (Box 9)
    - Interim Remedial Measures Seep Abatement (letter and workplan), September 2008 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2.2: Status Reports
    - Status Reports, June 2005 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Bound Report 6, June-September 2005 (Box 9)
    - Bound Reports 7-11, January-May 2007 (Box 9)
    - Bound Reports 1-10, June 2007 - March 2008 (Box 10)
    - Bound Reports 1-9, April-December 2008 (Box 11)
    - Bound Report 10, January-March 2009 (Box 11)
    - Bound Report 1, April-June 2009 (Box 12)
    - Bound Report 2, July-September 2009 (Box 12)
    - Bound Report 3, October-December 2009 (Box 12)
    - Bound Report 4, April-June 2011 (Box 12)
    - Bound Report 1, July-September 2012 (Box 13)
    - Bound Report 2, January-March 2010 (Box 13)
- NYSDEC
  This series consists of overall project documentation on compact discs.
  - Project Record for FOIL Requests (4 discs), 2006 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Public project Record as of June 30, 2008 (2 discs) (Box 13, Folder 2)